<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
    <channel>
        <title>Posts on Jakob Klemm - Database</title>
        <link>https://wiki.jeykey.net/posts/</link>
        <description>Recent content in Posts on Jakob Klemm - Database</description>
        <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
        <language>en-us</language>
        <copyright>&lt;a href=&#34;https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;CC BY-NC 4.0&lt;/a&gt;</copyright>
        <lastBuildDate>Thu, 03 Jun 2021 12:18:24 +0200</lastBuildDate>
        <atom:link href="https://wiki.jeykey.net/posts/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
        
        <item>
            <title>Friction</title>
            <link>https://wiki.jeykey.net/posts/friction/</link>
            <pubDate>Thu, 03 Jun 2021 12:18:24 +0200</pubDate>
            
            <guid>https://wiki.jeykey.net/posts/friction/</guid>
            <description>(Not physical forces, but friction in human behavior.) Humans only do what is easy and convenient for them. They try to avoid more friction at any cost.
In order to achieve anything it is important to reduce the fiction of it as much as possible.
 An action has less friction if it fits in our current flow, our current routine or structure. Addition by subtraction Remove anything that is not directly helpful for the end goal.</description>
            <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>(Not physical forces, but friction in human behavior.)
Humans only do what is easy and convenient for them. They try to
avoid more friction at any cost.</p>
<p>In order to achieve anything it is important to reduce the fiction of
it as much as possible.</p>
<ul>
<li>An action has less friction if it fits in our current flow, our
current routine or structure.</li>
<li>Addition by subtraction
Remove anything that is not directly helpful for the end goal. By
doing this you can remove as much friction as possible and focus on
what really matters. This is done by adjusting the environment and
creating one, where doing the right thing is as easy as possible.</li>
<li>Prime the environment for immediate use. Already place the items
needed for the next task in a visible location. This also works as a
cue.</li>
</ul>
]]></content>
        </item>
        
        <item>
            <title>Habits</title>
            <link>https://wiki.jeykey.net/posts/habits/</link>
            <pubDate>Thu, 03 Jun 2021 12:17:26 +0200</pubDate>
            
            <guid>https://wiki.jeykey.net/posts/habits/</guid>
            <description>Most of what we do on a day to day basis isn&amp;rsquo;t something we want to do. We do it because we hope that it can help us to achieve what we really want. Most habits and actions are in a sens just obstacles. We only really want what the habit or action produces or delivers.
In order to learn new habits and keep repeating existing ones a few things are important: Habits are triggered by cues, so it is important to Make it obvious.</description>
            <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Most of what we do on a day to day basis isn&rsquo;t something we want to
do. We do it because we hope that it can help us to achieve what we
really want. Most habits and actions are in a sens just obstacles. We
only really want what the habit or action produces or delivers.</p>
<p>In order to learn new habits and keep repeating existing ones a few
things are important: Habits are triggered by cues, so it is important
to <a href="/posts/make_it_obvious/">Make it obvious</a>. Once a habit is triggered it is important to give
a reason to do it, to <a href="/posts/make_it_attractive/">Make it attractive</a>. Humans always chose the path
of least resistance, meaning just because something is attractive, it
might not be enough to trick ourselves into doing it. That&rsquo;s why it is
important to <a href="make_it_easy">Make it easy</a>.</p>
<p>Up to now we have looked at tactics to get us started with a habit and
actually do it. But what turns actions into habits is repetition. In
order to stay consistent with our habits, we need to <a href="/posts/make_it_satisfying/">Make it satisfying</a>.</p>
<p>In case the system ever breaks down and the chain of repetitions is
broken, it is important to follow the <a href="/posts/two_day_rule/">Two-Day Rule</a> for an easy
recovery.</p>
]]></content>
        </item>
        
        <item>
            <title>Dopamine</title>
            <link>https://wiki.jeykey.net/posts/dopamine/</link>
            <pubDate>Fri, 16 Apr 2021 11:02:27 +0200</pubDate>
            
            <guid>https://wiki.jeykey.net/posts/dopamine/</guid>
            <description>Dopamine is often associated with pleasure. But it is also released when pleasure is anticipated. If your dopamine level rises, so does your motivation to act.
This can be utilized in two different ways:
 Using the dopamine of one task can be used to get the next one started (Habit stacking). Connecting a positive habit with a negative one (Temptation bundling).  But this can lead to over expectation, like being more excited about ordering and selecting a new product then when you actually have it and get to use it.</description>
            <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Dopamine is often associated with pleasure. But it is also released
when pleasure is anticipated. If your dopamine level rises, so does
your motivation to act.</p>
<p>This can be utilized in two different ways:</p>
<ul>
<li>Using the dopamine of one task can be used to get the next one
started (<a href="/posts/habit_stacking/">Habit stacking</a>).</li>
<li>Connecting a positive habit with a negative one (<a href="/posts/temptation_bundling/">Temptation
bundling</a>).</li>
</ul>
<p>But this can lead to over expectation, like being more excited about
ordering and selecting a new product then when you actually have it
and get to use it.</p>
]]></content>
        </item>
        
        <item>
            <title>Socia media</title>
            <link>https://wiki.jeykey.net/posts/socia_media/</link>
            <pubDate>Wed, 14 Apr 2021 11:07:31 +0200</pubDate>
            
            <guid>https://wiki.jeykey.net/posts/socia_media/</guid>
            <description>The goal of social media sites is not to connect people or to enhance their lives, the goal is to reduce their users freedom of choice in order to increase their profits. Through data these companies can make choices for you, present them with their choice and still give you the feeling of being in control.
This can quickly lead to a feedback loop, where companies and platforms work together and feed their products directly to customers without using the free market and ignoring the principles of Capitalism.</description>
            <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>The goal of social media sites is not to connect people or to enhance
their lives, the goal is to reduce their users freedom of choice in
order to increase their profits. Through data these companies can make
choices for you, present them with their choice and still give you the
feeling of being in control.</p>
<p>This can quickly lead to a feedback loop, where companies and
platforms work together and feed their products directly to customers
without using the free market and ignoring the principles of <a href="/posts/capitalism/">Capitalism</a>.</p>
]]></content>
        </item>
        
        <item>
            <title>Habit tracker</title>
            <link>https://wiki.jeykey.net/posts/habit_tracker/</link>
            <pubDate>Fri, 02 Apr 2021 11:03:38 +0200</pubDate>
            
            <guid>https://wiki.jeykey.net/posts/habit_tracker/</guid>
            <description>While a task itself might not provide satisfaction, seeing progress is. One easy form of immediate gratification might be to visualize and measure each repetition and show the progress. After a certain number of repetitions, breaking the chain becomes a reason to keep the habit going.
Just seeing progress being made often is enough motivation to keep going. With each step the desire to continue grows. In addition a habit tracker makes it more difficult to lie to yourself and live in an illusion or distorted view of the world.</description>
            <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>While a task itself might not provide satisfaction, seeing progress
is. One easy form of immediate gratification might be to visualize and
measure each repetition and show the progress. After a certain number
of repetitions, <em>breaking the chain</em> becomes a reason to keep the habit
going.</p>
<p>Just seeing progress being made often is enough motivation to keep
going. With each step the desire to continue grows. In addition a
habit tracker makes it more difficult to lie to yourself and live in
an illusion or distorted view of the world.</p>
<p>An easy example of a habit tracker might be the visual Github Commit
Overview. The fear of seeing an empty square can be motivation enough
to keep regular commits going.</p>
<p>At first glance habit tracking might seem like an additional habit
that now also needs to be internalized. Preferably the tracking should
be fully automated (like on Github), but if thats not possible it
might be helpful to use <a href="/posts/habit_stacking/">Habit stacking</a> to trigger the tracking of a
habit after the habit itself.</p>
]]></content>
        </item>
        
        <item>
            <title>Temptation bundling</title>
            <link>https://wiki.jeykey.net/posts/temptation_bundling/</link>
            <pubDate>Wed, 24 Mar 2021 11:07:40 +0200</pubDate>
            
            <guid>https://wiki.jeykey.net/posts/temptation_bundling/</guid>
            <description>In order to get things you have to do done it is possible to connect them to a habit you want to do.
It can be even better to connect temptation bundling with Habit stacking, to create a new system with three components: A current habit -&amp;gt; Something you have to do -&amp;gt; Something you want to do.
If these two actions are done together often enough it becomes natural to do the obligation before the joy.</description>
            <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>In order to get things you have to do done it is possible to connect
them to a habit you want to do.</p>
<p>It can be even better to connect temptation bundling with <a href="/posts/habit_stacking/">Habit
stacking</a>, to create a new system with three components: A current
habit -&gt; Something you have to do -&gt; Something you want to do.</p>
<p>If these two actions are done together often enough it becomes natural
to do the obligation before the joy.</p>
]]></content>
        </item>
        
        <item>
            <title>Habit stacking</title>
            <link>https://wiki.jeykey.net/posts/habit_stacking/</link>
            <pubDate>Wed, 24 Mar 2021 11:03:34 +0200</pubDate>
            
            <guid>https://wiki.jeykey.net/posts/habit_stacking/</guid>
            <description>Instead of trying to attach a habit to a situation, place or time, it can be easier to attach it to an existing habit. This has a few advantages:
 You are already in an habit-mindset, making the transition easier. The decision of what to do next is heavily influenced by what we just did / completed. (The Diderot effect) describes a similar behavior, but in the context of spending habits and spirals.</description>
            <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Instead of trying to attach a habit to a situation, place or time, it
can be easier to attach it to an existing habit. This has a few
advantages:</p>
<ul>
<li>You are already in an <em>habit-mindset</em>, making the transition easier.</li>
<li>The decision of what to do next is heavily influenced by what we
just did / completed. (The <a href="/posts/diderot_effect/">Diderot effect</a>) describes a similar
behavior, but in the context of spending habits and spirals.)</li>
<li>After successfully completing a task you can profit of the natural
momentum that comes from that and directly use it for the next task.</li>
</ul>
]]></content>
        </item>
        
        <item>
            <title>Two-Day Rule</title>
            <link>https://wiki.jeykey.net/posts/two_day_rule/</link>
            <pubDate>Tue, 23 Mar 2021 11:08:16 +0200</pubDate>
            
            <guid>https://wiki.jeykey.net/posts/two_day_rule/</guid>
            <description>If a habit breaks down and a repetition is missed it is important to follow the Two-Day Rule, which states that you can never miss two repetitions in a row.
Missing more than one repetition in a row is dangerous, because the habit of not doing the habit can build quickly. As soon as one streak ends, one chain is broken, the next one is started immediately.</description>
            <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>If a habit breaks down and a repetition is missed it is important to
follow the <code>Two-Day Rule</code>, which states that you can never miss two
repetitions in a row.</p>
<p>Missing more than one repetition in a row is dangerous, because the
<strong>habit of not doing the habit</strong> can build quickly. As soon as one streak
ends, one chain is broken, the next one is started immediately.</p>
]]></content>
        </item>
        
        <item>
            <title>Sidewinder</title>
            <link>https://wiki.jeykey.net/posts/sidewinder/</link>
            <pubDate>Tue, 23 Mar 2021 11:07:28 +0200</pubDate>
            
            <guid>https://wiki.jeykey.net/posts/sidewinder/</guid>
            <description>Die AIM-9 Sidewinder war die erste wärmesuchende Luft zu Luft Rakete der Welt. Sie wurde unter extremer Geheimhaltung entwickelt und war der Soviet Union Jahre voraus.
Während der chinesischen Offensive gegen Taiwan unterstützen beide Seiten den Konflikt. Mit den MiG-17 Flugzeugen hatte China den klaren Vorteil, da Taiwan nicht im Besitz von Waffen oder Flugzeugen mit einer ähnlichen Maximalhöhe war. Im geheimen bekam Taiwan einige Sidewinder-Raketen und das nötige Training. In den Luftkämpfen wurden zum ersten mal gelenkte Luft-Luft-Raketen eingesetzt.</description>
            <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Die <code>AIM-9 Sidewinder</code> war die erste wärmesuchende Luft zu Luft Rakete
der Welt. Sie wurde unter extremer Geheimhaltung entwickelt und war
der Soviet Union Jahre voraus.</p>
<p>Während der chinesischen Offensive gegen Taiwan unterstützen beide
Seiten den Konflikt. Mit den MiG-17 Flugzeugen hatte China den klaren
Vorteil, da Taiwan nicht im Besitz von Waffen oder Flugzeugen mit
einer ähnlichen Maximalhöhe war. Im geheimen bekam Taiwan einige
Sidewinder-Raketen und das nötige Training. In den Luftkämpfen wurden
zum ersten mal gelenkte Luft-Luft-Raketen eingesetzt.</p>
<p>Während den Kämpfen blieb eine der Raketen in einem chinesischen
Flugzeug stecken und konnte analysiert werden. Daraufhin entwickelte
die UDSSR ihre eigene Lenkfeuerwaffe. Bereits wenige Jahre später
wurde die <code>K-13</code> eingesetzt und wurde zur am weitest verbreiteten
Luft-Luft-Rakete der Welt. Zwar waren die USA technisch immer noch
im Vorteil, aber die Fehler über Taiwan schufen gleiche Bedingungen in
zukünftigen Luft-Konflikten.</p>
]]></content>
        </item>
        
        <item>
            <title>Optimal stopping</title>
            <link>https://wiki.jeykey.net/posts/optimal_stopping/</link>
            <pubDate>Tue, 23 Mar 2021 11:07:07 +0200</pubDate>
            
            <guid>https://wiki.jeykey.net/posts/optimal_stopping/</guid>
            <description>In a sequence of options where you can only ever decide on the current one it is important to know when to stop.
While there are exceptions the important number is 37%.
If the task is to purchase a house, then the first 37% of them should be reviewed but not actually considered. After that threshold has been passed, the next best house has to be bought. The rules for that aren&amp;rsquo;t as exact, but if the item can be measured using comparable numbers it should be better than any previous.</description>
            <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>In a sequence of options where you can only ever decide on the current
one it is important to know when to stop.</p>
<p>While there are exceptions the important number is <code>37%</code>.</p>
<p>If the task is to purchase a house, then the first <code>37%</code> of them should
be reviewed but not actually considered. After that threshold has been
passed, the next best house has to be bought. The rules for that
aren&rsquo;t as exact, but if the item can be measured using comparable
numbers it should be better than any previous.</p>
<p>(Statistically that is not always possible, since the best one might
have been in the first <code>37%</code>, but overall it should work out.)</p>
]]></content>
        </item>
        
        <item>
            <title>Make it obvious</title>
            <link>https://wiki.jeykey.net/posts/make_it_obvious/</link>
            <pubDate>Tue, 23 Mar 2021 11:06:38 +0200</pubDate>
            
            <guid>https://wiki.jeykey.net/posts/make_it_obvious/</guid>
            <description>In order to start / trigger a habit without having to waste brain power on it is effective to use cues, which are connected to the individual habits. It is possible to attach new habits to existing ones using Habit stacking or to attach them to specific events or situations using a Implementation intention Through out all of them it is much more important to focus on the external Environment instead of yourself.</description>
            <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>In order to start / trigger a habit without having to waste brain
power on it is effective to use cues, which are connected to the
individual habits. It is possible to attach new habits to existing
ones using <a href="/posts/habit_stacking/">Habit stacking</a> or to attach them to specific events or
situations using a <a href="/posts/implementation_intention/">Implementation intention</a> Through out all of them it
is much more important to focus on the external <a href="/posts/environment/">Environment</a> instead of
yourself.</p>
]]></content>
        </item>
        
        <item>
            <title>Make it easy</title>
            <link>https://wiki.jeykey.net/posts/make_it_easy/</link>
            <pubDate>Tue, 23 Mar 2021 11:05:59 +0200</pubDate>
            
            <guid>https://wiki.jeykey.net/posts/make_it_easy/</guid>
            <description>Most of the time we are so focused on how to do something in the optimal way, that we don&amp;rsquo;t actually do it. James Clear describes it as Motion or Action. You feel like you are getting something done, but your actually only planning to get something done.
But why aren&amp;rsquo;t all habits easy? Humans always choose the path of least resistance. They always try to minimize Friction.
A lot of the decisions we make every day are just habits.</description>
            <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Most of the time we are so focused on how to do something in the
optimal way, that we don&rsquo;t actually do it. James Clear describes it as
<a href="/posts/motion_or_action/">Motion or Action</a>. You feel like you are getting something done, but
your actually only planning to get something done.</p>
<p>But why aren&rsquo;t all habits easy?
Humans always choose the path of least resistance. They always try to
minimize <a href="/posts/friction/">Friction</a>.</p>
<p>A lot of the decisions we make every day are just habits. While we do
the more influential, important ones consciously, the habits that came
before them influenced the situation in which the important decisions
have to be made. A habit that can be completed in just a few seconds
can influence every decision that comes after it. Each day there are a
few <a href="/posts/decisive_moments/">Decisive moments</a>, that influence the rest of the day.</p>
<p>Instead of trying to master something instantly or learning a
complicated habit, it might be helpful to start with something
simpler, following <a href="/posts/two_minute_rule/">Two-Minute Rule</a>.</p>
<p>Instead of making a good habit easy it might also be important to make
a bad habit difficult: <a href="/posts/make_it_difficult/">Make it difficult</a>.</p>
]]></content>
        </item>
        
        <item>
            <title>Make it difficult</title>
            <link>https://wiki.jeykey.net/posts/make_it_difficult/</link>
            <pubDate>Tue, 23 Mar 2021 11:05:56 +0200</pubDate>
            
            <guid>https://wiki.jeykey.net/posts/make_it_difficult/</guid>
            <description>While good habits are important for success, in most situations not having bad habits can be enough.
Instead of using willpower to fight against temptation it might be helpful to use a Commitment device, in order to automate the decision and remove any human error from it.</description>
            <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>While good habits are important for success, in most situations not
having bad habits can be enough.</p>
<p>Instead of using willpower to fight against temptation it might be
helpful to use a <a href="/posts/commitment_device/">Commitment device</a>, in order to automate the decision
and remove any human error from it.</p>
]]></content>
        </item>
        
        <item>
            <title>Make it attractive</title>
            <link>https://wiki.jeykey.net/posts/make_it_attractive/</link>
            <pubDate>Tue, 23 Mar 2021 11:05:53 +0200</pubDate>
            
            <guid>https://wiki.jeykey.net/posts/make_it_attractive/</guid>
            <description>Humans are rewarded the easiest using Dopamine, since it is the humans natural way of reward. The issue is that the natural reward system can be used in both directions the same way, meaning good habits use the same reward system as bad ones.
If dopamine is still not enough to learn a new difficult habit you can change your Habit perspective on it.
It can also be easier to do learn a habit, if it is the social norm or enforced through culture.</description>
            <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Humans are rewarded the easiest using <a href="/posts/dopamine/">Dopamine</a>, since it is the humans
natural way of reward. The issue is that the natural reward system can
be used in both directions the same way, meaning good habits use the
same reward system as bad ones.</p>
<p>If dopamine is still not enough to learn a new difficult habit you can
change your <a href="/posts/habit_perspective/">Habit perspective</a> on it.</p>
<p>It can also be easier to do learn a habit, if it is the social norm or
enforced through culture. This is highly effective, since humans are
herd animals.</p>
<p>We imitate the behavior of three groups:</p>
<ul>
<li><a href="/posts/the_close/">The close</a></li>
<li><a href="/posts/the_many/">The many</a></li>
<li><a href="/posts/the_powerful/">The powerful</a></li>
</ul>
<p>Another possibility utilizing <a href="/posts/the_close/">The close</a> might be inform somebody about
your new habit. This can then make it difficult to break a habit,
since it would disappoint the other person. If simply informing them
is not enough a <a href="/posts/habit_contract/">Habit contract</a> can be used.</p>
<p>It is also important to understand <code>Why?</code> you are doing it (or
anything), so you need to understand your <a href="/posts/motivation/">Motivation</a>.</p>
]]></content>
        </item>
        
        <item>
            <title>Locus of control</title>
            <link>https://wiki.jeykey.net/posts/locus_of_control/</link>
            <pubDate>Tue, 23 Mar 2021 11:05:50 +0200</pubDate>
            
            <guid>https://wiki.jeykey.net/posts/locus_of_control/</guid>
            <description>While our lives are shaped a lot by external forces and events or people that are outside our control, some people believe that we can still manifest our own destiny and take control over our own lives. The degree to which people believe things are within their control is called Locus of control and it is often referred to as a key factor of success.
If you simply believe your live to be miserable because other people or your environment makes you miserable, you will have no motivation or reason to change and take initiative.</description>
            <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>While our lives are shaped a lot by external forces and events or
people that are outside our control, some people believe that we can
still manifest our own destiny and take control over our own lives.
The degree to which people believe things are within their control is
called <code>Locus of control</code> and it is often referred to as a key factor of
success.</p>
<p>If you simply believe your live to be miserable because other people
or your environment makes you miserable, you will have no motivation
or reason to change and take initiative. But by realizing that we are
in full control of our lives it is also possible to change your
perspective on the elements that many people consider responsible for
their misery. Instead of viewing them as external forces that are
against your own plans, that are against you, you can view them as
opportunities and new perspectives on the world.</p>
<blockquote>
<p>With an internal locus of control it will feel less like live is
happening and more like live is happening due to you. Joey Schweitzer
(<a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=B-L8CYwglj4&amp;ab%5Fchannel=BetterIdeas">https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=B-L8CYwglj4&amp;ab%5Fchannel=BetterIdeas</a>)</p>
</blockquote>
]]></content>
        </item>
        
        <item>
            <title>Habit contract</title>
            <link>https://wiki.jeykey.net/posts/habit_contract/</link>
            <pubDate>Tue, 23 Mar 2021 11:03:22 +0200</pubDate>
            
            <guid>https://wiki.jeykey.net/posts/habit_contract/</guid>
            <description>If someone has authority over you it is usual to follow their orders, even when there is no direct advantage or only a delayed one.
But habits are inherently different. They are agreements with yourself, so you do something that you hope will have an advantage for you in the future. Sadly &amp;ldquo;you&amp;rdquo; don&amp;rsquo;t really have any authority over yourself. Most people wouldn&amp;rsquo;t say they treat themselves as an well as they treat others.</description>
            <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>If someone has authority over you it is usual to follow their orders,
even when there is no direct advantage or only a delayed one.</p>
<p>But habits are inherently different. They are agreements with
yourself, so you do something that you hope will have an advantage for
you in the future. Sadly <em>&ldquo;you&rdquo;</em> don&rsquo;t really have any authority over
yourself. Most people wouldn&rsquo;t say they treat themselves as an
well as they treat others.</p>
<p>In order to stick with difficult habits it might be helpful to use a
<code>Habit contract</code>. Once the decision has been made to adopt a new habit,
it is easy to create a contract with somebody else. That person is
then the authority over you for that specific habit.
(There are even sites and tools that make this process simple and
allow money to be invested, increasing the stakes.)</p>
<p>If a proper contract is too much work it might be enough to simply
tell somebody about your new habit or your goals. The thought of
disappointing them could be enough to motivate somebody.</p>
]]></content>
        </item>
        
        <item>
            <title>Two Book System</title>
            <link>https://wiki.jeykey.net/posts/two_book_system/</link>
            <pubDate>Mon, 15 Mar 2021 11:08:13 +0200</pubDate>
            
            <guid>https://wiki.jeykey.net/posts/two_book_system/</guid>
            <description>(https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=oaTcicNDpQc&amp;amp;ab%5Fchannel=R.C.Waldun) Some books are really hard to read and it is easy to lose motivation. The Two Book System proposes a way of ensuring continued reading no matter the book. This is especially helpful for assignments or necessary reading instead of for fun reading.
 Stretch-Book: The Stretch-Book is the difficult one. It is complex and often not fun to read. This book should still be interesting and there should be a reason to read it, but it usually contains passages that are boring or difficult to understand, making long reading sessions draining.</description>
            <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>(<a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=oaTcicNDpQc&amp;ab%5Fchannel=R.C.Waldun">https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=oaTcicNDpQc&amp;ab%5Fchannel=R.C.Waldun</a>)
Some books are really hard to read and it is easy to lose motivation.
The <code>Two Book System</code> proposes a way of ensuring continued reading no
matter the book. This is especially helpful for assignments or
necessary reading instead of <em>for fun</em> reading.</p>
<ul>
<li>Stretch-Book: The <code>Stretch-Book</code> is the difficult one. It is complex
and often <em>not fun</em> to read. This book should still be interesting and
there should be a reason to read it, but it usually contains
passages that are boring or difficult to understand, making long
reading sessions draining.</li>
<li>Keep-Book: If reading the <code>Stretch-Book</code> ever gets too much or a pause
is needed, the <code>Keep-Book</code> is used. It should be light and easy,
whilst also being interesting and useful. While Novels are great for
this, the <code>Keep-Book</code> might be used for shorter sessions, making an
overly complex story difficult to switch.</li>
</ul>
]]></content>
        </item>
        
        <item>
            <title>The many</title>
            <link>https://wiki.jeykey.net/posts/the_many/</link>
            <pubDate>Sun, 14 Mar 2021 11:07:59 +0200</pubDate>
            
            <guid>https://wiki.jeykey.net/posts/the_many/</guid>
            <description>Even if the people around us aren&amp;rsquo;t close to us we can easily feel peer pressured by them or follow their behavior. We constantly look to at our Environment on how to act. Even when we know that the group is wrong we would rather be wrong with the crowd rather than right alone.</description>
            <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Even if the people around us aren&rsquo;t close to us we can easily feel
peer pressured by them or follow their behavior. We constantly look to
at our <a href="/posts/environment/">Environment</a> on how to act. Even when we know that the group is
wrong we would rather be wrong with the crowd rather than right alone.</p>
]]></content>
        </item>
        
        <item>
            <title>Solutionismus</title>
            <link>https://wiki.jeykey.net/posts/solutionismus/</link>
            <pubDate>Fri, 12 Mar 2021 11:07:34 +0200</pubDate>
            
            <guid>https://wiki.jeykey.net/posts/solutionismus/</guid>
            <description>Mit dem Klimawandel haben wir das zentrale Problem unserer Zeit vor uns. Während viele neue Gesetze, neue Regulationen und aufgezwungene soziale Änderungen verlangen, gibt es eine Alternative.
Der Grund wieso wir in dieser Situation gelandet sind ist Fortschritt und wissenschaftliche Entwicklungen. Durch die industrielle Revolution und unsere Abhängigkeit von Öl sind wurden unglaubliche Mengen an Geld generiert und Vermögen gemacht. Wenn es nun an der Zeit ist das nächste Zeitalter zu starten gibt es neue, viel grössere Summen zu machen.</description>
            <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Mit dem Klimawandel haben wir das zentrale Problem unserer Zeit vor
uns. Während viele neue Gesetze, neue Regulationen und aufgezwungene
soziale Änderungen verlangen, gibt es eine Alternative.</p>
<p>Der Grund wieso wir in dieser Situation gelandet sind ist Fortschritt
und wissenschaftliche Entwicklungen. Durch die industrielle Revolution
und unsere Abhängigkeit von Öl sind wurden unglaubliche Mengen an Geld
generiert und Vermögen gemacht. Wenn es nun an der Zeit ist das
nächste Zeitalter zu starten gibt es neue, viel grössere Summen zu
machen. Sobald genügend Menschen realisieren, dass der Klimawandel
nicht einfach eine Gefahr, sondern eine riesige Chance ist, wird die
Geschwindigkeit wissenschaftlicher Entwicklungen wieder zunehmen,
ähnlich wie in Kriegszeiten.</p>
]]></content>
        </item>
        
        <item>
            <title>Flow state</title>
            <link>https://wiki.jeykey.net/posts/flow_state/</link>
            <pubDate>Mon, 08 Mar 2021 11:02:52 +0200</pubDate>
            
            <guid>https://wiki.jeykey.net/posts/flow_state/</guid>
            <description>The most productive state a person can be in is called Flow state. In it people often lose their sense of time and fully focus on one task. In order to achieve flow state the task at hand needs to have the right level of difficulty:
 With easy tasks people become bored easily. Difficult tasks create frustration.  In order to get into and stay in flow state a task should have a difficulty of 4% beyond the current level.</description>
            <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>The most productive state a person can be in is called Flow state. In
it people often lose their sense of time and fully focus on one task.
In order to achieve flow state the task at hand needs to have the
right level of difficulty:</p>
<ul>
<li>With easy tasks people become bored easily.</li>
<li>Difficult tasks create frustration.</li>
</ul>
<p>In order to get into and stay in flow state a task should have a
difficulty of <em>4%</em> beyond the current level. When a task is slightly
outside the current ability, the brain needs to actually think and
improve in order to achieve it.</p>
]]></content>
        </item>
        
        <item>
            <title>Natural behavior</title>
            <link>https://wiki.jeykey.net/posts/natural_behavior/</link>
            <pubDate>Sun, 21 Feb 2021 11:07:03 +0200</pubDate>
            
            <guid>https://wiki.jeykey.net/posts/natural_behavior/</guid>
            <description>It has always be important to have accurate data about people. But historic methods were not evaluating natural behavior. Instead they were using tools with a high possibility of Cognitive bias.
With modern technology it is possible to capture the natural behavior of users. Online users don&amp;rsquo;t feel spied on and feel save. Therefore the recorded behavior is more accurate and natural.</description>
            <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>It has always be important to have accurate data about people. But
historic methods were not evaluating natural behavior. Instead they
were using tools with a high possibility of <a href="/posts/cognitive_bias/">Cognitive bias</a>.</p>
<p>With modern technology it is possible to capture the natural behavior
of users. Online users don&rsquo;t feel spied on and feel save. Therefore
the recorded behavior is more accurate and natural.</p>
]]></content>
        </item>
        
        <item>
            <title>Thermal exhaust port</title>
            <link>https://wiki.jeykey.net/posts/thermal_exhaust_port/</link>
            <pubDate>Fri, 12 Feb 2021 11:08:09 +0200</pubDate>
            
            <guid>https://wiki.jeykey.net/posts/thermal_exhaust_port/</guid>
            <description>A single small flaw in an otherwise flawless system. The idea comes from the death star with its single exhaust port that was exploitable and destroyed the entire base.</description>
            <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>A single small flaw in an otherwise flawless system. The idea comes
from the death star with its single exhaust port that was exploitable
and destroyed the entire base.</p>
]]></content>
        </item>
        
        <item>
            <title>Gerasimov-Doktrin</title>
            <link>https://wiki.jeykey.net/posts/gerasimov_doktrin/</link>
            <pubDate>Thu, 11 Feb 2021 11:03:14 +0200</pubDate>
            
            <guid>https://wiki.jeykey.net/posts/gerasimov_doktrin/</guid>
            <description>Die Ideen von Walerij Gerassimov (Chef des russischen Genealstabs) beschreiben eine neue Art der Kriegsführung:
 Lage vor einem militärischen Konflikt kann man bereits anfangen die Bevölkerung zu beeinflussen und Unterstützung zu gewinnen. Neue Technologien erlauben zielgerichtete Propaganda (Cambridge Analytica). Die Strategien sind stark asymmetrisch und erfordern gute Daten sowie eine gute Verteilinfrastruktur (Socia media).   Die Regeln des Krieges haben sich verändert. Die Rolle der nicht-militärischen Mittel, um politische und strategische Ziele zu erreichen, ist grösser geworden.</description>
            <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Die Ideen von Walerij Gerassimov (Chef des russischen Genealstabs)
beschreiben eine neue Art der Kriegsführung:</p>
<ul>
<li>Lage vor einem militärischen Konflikt kann man bereits anfangen die
Bevölkerung zu beeinflussen und Unterstützung zu gewinnen.</li>
<li>Neue Technologien erlauben zielgerichtete Propaganda (Cambridge
Analytica).</li>
<li>Die Strategien sind stark asymmetrisch und erfordern gute Daten
sowie eine gute Verteilinfrastruktur (<a href="/posts/socia_media/">Socia media)</a>.</li>
</ul>
<blockquote>
<p>Die Regeln des Krieges haben sich verändert. Die Rolle der
nicht-militärischen Mittel, um politische und strategische Ziele zu
erreichen, ist grösser geworden. - Gerassimov</p>
</blockquote>
]]></content>
        </item>
        
        <item>
            <title>Asymmetric systems</title>
            <link>https://wiki.jeykey.net/posts/asymmetric_systems/</link>
            <pubDate>Wed, 10 Feb 2021 22:09:12 +0200</pubDate>
            
            <guid>https://wiki.jeykey.net/posts/asymmetric_systems/</guid>
            <description>Modern services use algorithms to learn more about their users. But through secrecy and complexity users know very little about these systems. Companies then use that to get even more data from their users.
Through the missing knowledge about the inner workings users are easily exploited, ether as customers for financial gains or in order to increase foreign influence through Digital Colonialism.</description>
            <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Modern services use algorithms to learn more about their users. But
through secrecy and complexity users know very little about these
systems. Companies then use that to get even more data from their
users.</p>
<p>Through the missing knowledge about the inner workings users are
easily exploited, ether as customers for financial gains or in order
to increase foreign influence through <a href="/posts/digital_colonialism/">Digital Colonialism</a>.</p>
]]></content>
        </item>
        
        <item>
            <title>Potemkinsches Dorf</title>
            <link>https://wiki.jeykey.net/posts/potemkinsches_dorf/</link>
            <pubDate>Wed, 10 Feb 2021 11:07:10 +0200</pubDate>
            
            <guid>https://wiki.jeykey.net/posts/potemkinsches_dorf/</guid>
            <description>Als Zarin Katharina die Grosse die Dörfer Russlands besuchen ging wurden extra für sie Kulissendörfer aufgebaut um den Eindruck einer besseren Gegend zu schaffen.
Auch heute wird der Begriff noch angewendet wenn Politiker oder Mächtige den Zustand von etwas Schlechtem verstecken wollen und es mit viel Aufwand wie etwas Gutes aussehen lassen.</description>
            <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Als Zarin Katharina die Grosse die Dörfer Russlands besuchen ging
wurden extra für sie Kulissendörfer aufgebaut um den Eindruck einer
besseren Gegend zu schaffen.</p>
<p>Auch heute wird der Begriff noch angewendet wenn Politiker oder
Mächtige den Zustand von etwas Schlechtem verstecken wollen und es mit
viel Aufwand wie etwas Gutes aussehen lassen.</p>
]]></content>
        </item>
        
        <item>
            <title>Infinite scrolling</title>
            <link>https://wiki.jeykey.net/posts/infinite_scrolling/</link>
            <pubDate>Wed, 10 Feb 2021 11:05:44 +0200</pubDate>
            
            <guid>https://wiki.jeykey.net/posts/infinite_scrolling/</guid>
            <description>The motion of modern social media sites is a continuous scrolling without ever ending. This motion can be compared to slot machines, where the user would constantly pull down on a lever. But the two aren&amp;rsquo;t just similar in motion, they also serve the same purpose: They provide a simple, repetitive motion, to which users will get addicted.</description>
            <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>The motion of modern social media sites is a continuous scrolling
without ever ending. This motion can be compared to slot machines,
where the user would constantly pull down on a lever. But the two
aren&rsquo;t just similar in motion, they also serve the same purpose: They
provide a simple, repetitive motion, to which users will get addicted.</p>
]]></content>
        </item>
        
        <item>
            <title>Government</title>
            <link>https://wiki.jeykey.net/posts/government/</link>
            <pubDate>Wed, 10 Feb 2021 11:03:17 +0200</pubDate>
            
            <guid>https://wiki.jeykey.net/posts/government/</guid>
            <description>We are being raised to trust the institutions, to believe the people in power have our interests in mind and that their will always be a plan.
But in reality those institutions are made up of people, all with their own agendas and interests. So the only way to have long term prosperity for each individual is to let each individual be in charge of their own decisions and to keep government out of it as much as possible, while enforcing justice and morality not through laws but through principles (Kategorischer Imperativ (Immanuel Kant)).</description>
            <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>We are being raised to trust the institutions, to believe the people
in power have our interests in mind and that their will always be a
plan.</p>
<p>But in reality those institutions are made up of people, all with
their own agendas and interests. So the only way to have long term
prosperity for each individual is to let each individual be in charge
of their own decisions and to keep government out of it as much as
possible, while enforcing justice and morality not through laws but
through principles (Kategorischer Imperativ (<a href="/posts/immanuel_kant/">Immanuel Kant</a>)).</p>
]]></content>
        </item>
        
        <item>
            <title>Digital Colonialism</title>
            <link>https://wiki.jeykey.net/posts/digital_colonialism/</link>
            <pubDate>Wed, 10 Feb 2021 11:02:14 +0200</pubDate>
            
            <guid>https://wiki.jeykey.net/posts/digital_colonialism/</guid>
            <description>After the historic colonialism was abolished new ways were found for western countries to control and influence the rest of the world. While most resources flow from the third to the developed world, a few technologically advanced products come back. Through those western countries and individuals can heavily influence and profit of the developing world. Modern technologies also allow these powers to remain hidden, leaving the people in an illusion.</description>
            <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>After the historic colonialism was abolished new ways were found for
western countries to control and influence the rest of the world.
While most resources flow from the third to the developed world, a few
technologically advanced products come back. Through those western
countries and individuals can heavily influence and profit of the
developing world. Modern technologies also allow these powers to
remain hidden, leaving the people in an illusion.</p>
]]></content>
        </item>
        
        <item>
            <title>Cognitive bias</title>
            <link>https://wiki.jeykey.net/posts/cognitive_bias/</link>
            <pubDate>Wed, 10 Feb 2021 11:01:35 +0200</pubDate>
            
            <guid>https://wiki.jeykey.net/posts/cognitive_bias/</guid>
            <description>It could be argued that while an objective reality does exist it can never be used / discussed by humans, since they will always apply their own filter, their own bias.
But since no human knows objective reality the perspective with which someone looks at the world becomes important. Just by changing someones perspective (for example by asking a different question) they will have a new interpretation of reality.</description>
            <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>It could be argued that while an objective reality does exist it can
never be used / discussed by humans, since they will always apply
their own filter, their own bias.</p>
<p>But since no human knows objective reality the perspective with which
someone looks at the world becomes important. Just by changing
someones perspective (for example by asking a different question) they
will have a new interpretation of reality.</p>
]]></content>
        </item>
        
        <item>
            <title>Stoicism</title>
            <link>https://wiki.jeykey.net/posts/stoicism/</link>
            <pubDate>Mon, 08 Feb 2021 11:07:37 +0200</pubDate>
            
            <guid>https://wiki.jeykey.net/posts/stoicism/</guid>
            <description> Clear separation between things in and out of our control (Locus of control). 4 Virtues:  Courage Temperance Justice Wisdom   Principles: Principles for inner peace  </description>
            <content type="html"><![CDATA[<ul>
<li>Clear separation between things in and out of our control (<a href="/posts/locus_of_control/">Locus of
control</a>).</li>
<li>4 Virtues:
<ul>
<li>Courage</li>
<li>Temperance</li>
<li>Justice</li>
<li>Wisdom</li>
</ul>
</li>
<li>Principles: <a href="/posts/principles_inner_peace/">Principles for inner peace</a></li>
</ul>
]]></content>
        </item>
        
        <item>
            <title>Capitalism</title>
            <link>https://wiki.jeykey.net/posts/capitalism/</link>
            <pubDate>Sun, 31 Jan 2021 11:01:24 +0200</pubDate>
            
            <guid>https://wiki.jeykey.net/posts/capitalism/</guid>
            <description>The fundamental idea of capitalism consists of sovereign individuals owning capital.
This simple idea can be used to create incredible products, advance mankind and fulfill the lives of those individuals. The opposite is also true: Those who don&amp;rsquo;t constantly improve and innovate will fail and won&amp;rsquo;t survive. This is why capitalism has been responsible for most of our recent progress and has brought our standard of living to new heights.</description>
            <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>The fundamental idea of capitalism consists of sovereign individuals owning
capital.</p>
<p>This simple idea can be used to create incredible products, advance
mankind and fulfill the lives of those individuals. The opposite is
also true: Those who don&rsquo;t constantly improve and innovate will fail
and won&rsquo;t survive. This is why capitalism has been responsible for
most of our recent progress and has brought our standard of living to
new heights.</p>
<p>But capitalism is often criticized. In our current society greed and
exploitation is a common occurrence. But one could argue, that greed
itself is not a bad idea. But once people forget long term advantages
and opportunities and simply focus on themselves, have greed for
themselves in the current moment, bad things happen.
Not everybody has an end goal for live or a long term plan for their
future. But if they had they would realize that all non-sustainable,
exploitative behavior is not in their long term interest.</p>
]]></content>
        </item>
        
        <item>
            <title>Merkantilismus</title>
            <link>https://wiki.jeykey.net/posts/merkantilismus/</link>
            <pubDate>Mon, 25 Jan 2021 11:06:49 +0200</pubDate>
            
            <guid>https://wiki.jeykey.net/posts/merkantilismus/</guid>
            <description>Ein Wirtschaftssystem zwischen dem 16. und 17. Jahrhundert. Beschreibt starke Eingriffe des Staats in die Wirtschaft und in das Leben der Bürger. Das Ziel war die Maximierung des Reichtums des Staats und Steigerung der Handelskräfte. Dafür wurden vor allem Zölle und interne Regelungen eingeführt. Das System bevorzugte die Interessen des Staates über dem Wohl der Bürger. Merkantilismus ist einer der Gründe für die Abspaltung der USA von England.</description>
            <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Ein Wirtschaftssystem zwischen dem 16. und 17. Jahrhundert. Beschreibt starke
Eingriffe des Staats in die Wirtschaft und in das Leben der Bürger. Das Ziel war
die Maximierung des Reichtums des Staats und Steigerung der Handelskräfte. Dafür
wurden vor allem Zölle und interne Regelungen eingeführt. Das System bevorzugte
die Interessen des Staates über dem Wohl der Bürger. Merkantilismus ist einer
der Gründe für die Abspaltung der USA von England.</p>
]]></content>
        </item>
        
        <item>
            <title>Motivation</title>
            <link>https://wiki.jeykey.net/posts/motivation/</link>
            <pubDate>Sun, 24 Jan 2021 11:06:56 +0200</pubDate>
            
            <guid>https://wiki.jeykey.net/posts/motivation/</guid>
            <description>At the deepest, underlying level we only want to satisfy a few fundamental needs:
 Conserve energy Obtain food and water Find love and reproduce Connect and bond with others Win social acceptance and approval Reduce uncertainty Achieve status and prestige  Almost anything we do is to fulfill one of those needs. As a base state we also don&amp;rsquo;t ever act, unless we predict that in the short term we would be better of and could more easily meet one of our underlying desires.</description>
            <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>At the deepest, underlying level we only want to satisfy a few
fundamental needs:</p>
<ul>
<li>Conserve energy</li>
<li>Obtain food and water</li>
<li>Find love and reproduce</li>
<li>Connect and bond with others</li>
<li>Win social acceptance and approval</li>
<li>Reduce uncertainty</li>
<li>Achieve status and prestige</li>
</ul>
<p>Almost anything we do is to fulfill one of those needs. As a base
state we also don&rsquo;t ever act, unless we predict that in the short term
we would be better of and could more easily meet one of our underlying
desires. Most of what we do has no long term view and is only concerned
about the current moment. This was great for survival and
reproduction, but not for our current long term oriented system.</p>
]]></content>
        </item>
        
        <item>
            <title>Two-Minute Rule</title>
            <link>https://wiki.jeykey.net/posts/two_minute_rule/</link>
            <pubDate>Thu, 21 Jan 2021 11:08:19 +0200</pubDate>
            
            <guid>https://wiki.jeykey.net/posts/two_minute_rule/</guid>
            <description>When learning any new habit the initial task should take less than two minutes. While this approach doesn&amp;rsquo;t sound practical or helpful, it is important to understand, that a two-minute habit isn&amp;rsquo;t about mastering the craft or learning the skill. It is about learning to learn the skill. With the two-minute rule you learn the habit of showing up, of trying to learn something. Once that has been established, the habit can be improved, in order to learn the actual skill and achieve the goal.</description>
            <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>When learning any new habit the initial task should take less than two
minutes. While this approach doesn&rsquo;t sound practical or helpful, it is
important to understand, that a two-minute habit isn&rsquo;t about mastering
the craft or learning the skill.
It is about learning to learn the skill.
With the two-minute rule you learn the habit of showing up, of trying
to learn something. Once that has been established, the habit can be
improved, in order to learn the actual skill and achieve the goal.</p>
<p>This approach doesn&rsquo;t just work with small habits, since any life goal
can be expressed as a combination or chain of two-minute habits.</p>
]]></content>
        </item>
        
        <item>
            <title>The powerful</title>
            <link>https://wiki.jeykey.net/posts/the_powerful/</link>
            <pubDate>Thu, 21 Jan 2021 11:08:05 +0200</pubDate>
            
            <guid>https://wiki.jeykey.net/posts/the_powerful/</guid>
            <description>We spend a lot of time trying to fit in, be part of a group. But once were in, we start trying to stand out. For that we look to people that already stand out, most commonly the famous and powerful, in order to imitate their habits. It is quickly obvious that this can&amp;rsquo;t possibly work, since copying somebody with the goal of standing out is not feasible.</description>
            <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>We spend a lot of time trying to fit in, be part of a group. But once
were in, we start trying to stand out. For that we look to people that
already stand out, most commonly the famous and powerful, in order to
imitate their habits. It is quickly obvious that this can&rsquo;t possibly
work, since copying somebody with the goal of standing out is not
feasible.</p>
]]></content>
        </item>
        
        <item>
            <title>The close</title>
            <link>https://wiki.jeykey.net/posts/the_close/</link>
            <pubDate>Thu, 21 Jan 2021 11:07:43 +0200</pubDate>
            
            <guid>https://wiki.jeykey.net/posts/the_close/</guid>
            <description>Humans have evolved to life in tribes. We adapt the behavior of the people around us and feel easily peer pressured.
In order to learn a new habit or behavior it is easiest to join a group where the desired behavior is the normal behavior.
 Nothing sustains motivation better than belonging to the tribe. - James Clear (Atomic Habits, P.118)
 </description>
            <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Humans have evolved to life in tribes. We adapt the behavior of the
people around us and feel easily peer pressured.</p>
<p>In order to learn a new habit or behavior it is easiest to join a
group where the desired behavior is the normal behavior.</p>
<blockquote>
<p>Nothing sustains motivation better than belonging to the tribe. -
James Clear (Atomic Habits, P.118)</p>
</blockquote>
]]></content>
        </item>
        
        <item>
            <title>Self control</title>
            <link>https://wiki.jeykey.net/posts/self_control/</link>
            <pubDate>Thu, 21 Jan 2021 11:07:25 +0200</pubDate>
            
            <guid>https://wiki.jeykey.net/posts/self_control/</guid>
            <description>The people with the best self-control are typically the ones who need to use it the least. - James Clear (Atomic Habits, P.93)
 Instead of building willpower and self control in order to resist urges and feelings, it is easier to redesign the Environment, in order to have less triggers.
Physically removing food or other consumable goods is an easy first step. It is important to understand, that simply trying to build up the mental resilience to fight these urges is mostly pointless and highly inefficient.</description>
            <content type="html"><![CDATA[<blockquote>
<p>The people with the best self-control are typically the ones who need
to use it the least. - James Clear (Atomic Habits, P.93)</p>
</blockquote>
<p>Instead of building willpower and self control in order to resist
urges and feelings, it is easier to redesign the <a href="/posts/environment/">Environment</a>, in order
to have less triggers.</p>
<p>Physically removing food or other consumable goods is an easy first
step. It is important to understand, that simply trying to build up
the mental resilience to fight these urges is mostly pointless and
highly inefficient. But if there is no self control needed what so
ever there is also no danger of not having enough strength.</p>
<p>Self control is only a short-term strategy, not a long term one, since
it can be considered an <em>active process</em>. Properly designing your
environment on the other hand is a long term solution, because after
the environment is changed no more willpower or strength is needed to
resist bad cues.</p>
]]></content>
        </item>
        
        <item>
            <title>Sacrifice</title>
            <link>https://wiki.jeykey.net/posts/sacrifice/</link>
            <pubDate>Thu, 21 Jan 2021 11:07:21 +0200</pubDate>
            
            <guid>https://wiki.jeykey.net/posts/sacrifice/</guid>
            <description>Success is in most cases not determined by what skills you have our how much risk you take, but by how much you are willing to sacrifice now, to achieve something then.
Almost everything we consider significant in today&amp;rsquo;s world has a delayed gratification. For most of history humans lived in an environment of instant gratification, meaning good actions would be rewarded immediately (food and survival) and bad tasks would be punished immediately (death).</description>
            <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Success is in most cases not determined by what skills you have our
how much risk you take, but by how much you are willing to sacrifice
<strong>now</strong>, to achieve something <strong>then</strong>.</p>
<p>Almost everything we consider significant in today&rsquo;s world has a
delayed gratification. For most of history humans lived in an
environment of instant gratification, meaning good actions would be
rewarded immediately (food and survival) and bad tasks would be
punished immediately (death). But in our modern society success is a
long term strategy, not a spontaneous event.</p>
<p>For success you need the sacrifice immediate rewards no, in order to
get delayed rewards in the future. But most people spend their days
chasing instant gratification and are not able to wait for their long
term strategies to pay off.</p>
]]></content>
        </item>
        
        <item>
            <title>Principles for inner peace</title>
            <link>https://wiki.jeykey.net/posts/principles_inner_peace/</link>
            <pubDate>Thu, 21 Jan 2021 11:07:18 +0200</pubDate>
            
            <guid>https://wiki.jeykey.net/posts/principles_inner_peace/</guid>
            <description>7 Stoic principles for inner peace. (Einzelgänger - YouTube) Its not the events that disturb us. The world doesn&amp;rsquo;t disturb us.. Only the mind can do that. Not the events, but our own experience of them causes how we feel.To think one shouldn&amp;rsquo;t suffer or experience a loss shows that one is in denial of nature. Nature is outside of our control. The flow of events (Tao) is outside our control Most things have happened before.</description>
            <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>7 Stoic principles for inner peace. (Einzelgänger - YouTube)<!-- raw HTML omitted --></p>
<ol>
<li>Its not the events that disturb us.
<strong>The world doesn&rsquo;t disturb us.</strong>. Only the mind can do that. Not the events, but
our own experience of them causes how we feel.<!-- raw HTML omitted -->
To think one shouldn&rsquo;t suffer or experience a loss shows that one is in
denial of nature. Nature is outside of our control. The flow of events (Tao)
is outside our control</li>
<li>Most things have happened before.
We only have a limited view of live. We only think about what we have
experienced and seen. But the universe comes in cycles or waves. If we
haven&rsquo;t experienced a wave before, everything appears to be unprecedented.
But almost everything has happened before. (Meditations 7-49: Rhythm of events)</li>
<li>Our thoughts are unreliable.
Overthinking decisions and possible outcomes causes stress and anxiety but
achieves nothing. The future is outside our control.\\ (Excessive thinking)
<strong>We suffer more in often in imagination then in reality.</strong> - Seneca.</li>
<li>Adversity can make us stronger.
Going through misery and hardship isn&rsquo;t terrible or bad. It is outside our
control and part of the flow. But being able to thrive after all we have
been through is great. Don&rsquo;t focus on how bad things are but how we can get
through them.</li>
<li>The present is all we have.
Animals live in the moment.<!-- raw HTML omitted -->
Humans live in the past &amp; future. We worry about things outside our control.
The future and the past aren&rsquo;t real, they only exist in our thoughts. If we
don&rsquo;t think about them, don&rsquo;t worry about them, they don&rsquo;t exist.<!-- raw HTML omitted -->
This doesn&rsquo;t mean you shouldn&rsquo;t have memories or plans. But the past and the
future cannot touch us, we only exist in the present.</li>
<li>We&rsquo;re dying anyway.
At death the majority of death has already happened. Its a process over years
of our lives and it is inevitable. Spend your time well because you could die
any moment. -&gt; Live in the present.</li>
<li>In the grand scheme of things, we&rsquo;re not important.
Put life and all humans into perspective. Relative to the world and the
universe we are insignificant. Most of our decisions and thoughts make no
difference in the grand scheme of things.<!-- raw HTML omitted -->
But you can try to make a difference, leave your mark on the world and be
remembered.</li>
</ol>
]]></content>
        </item>
        
        <item>
            <title>Make it satisfying</title>
            <link>https://wiki.jeykey.net/posts/make_it_satisfying/</link>
            <pubDate>Thu, 21 Jan 2021 11:06:43 +0200</pubDate>
            
            <guid>https://wiki.jeykey.net/posts/make_it_satisfying/</guid>
            <description>Cardinal Rule of Behavior: What is rewarded is repeated. What is punished is avoided.
The habits that stick and the tasks that we repeat are determined by what we are rewarded for now. Sadly most habits that we would consider useful don&amp;rsquo;t have instant rewards. Instead they need to be repeated in order for the effects to show. Even worse: a lot of bad habits have instant gratification, while a lot of good habits don&amp;rsquo;t.</description>
            <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p><strong>Cardinal Rule of Behavior</strong>: <em>What is rewarded is repeated. What is
punished is avoided.</em></p>
<p>The habits that stick and the tasks that we repeat are determined by
what we are rewarded for now. Sadly most habits that we would consider
<em>useful</em> don&rsquo;t have instant rewards. Instead they need to be repeated in
order for the effects to show. Even worse: a lot of bad habits have
instant gratification, while a lot of good habits don&rsquo;t. In order to
adapt good habits and stick with them we need to <a href="/posts/sacrifice/">Sacrifice</a> and wait
for our delayed gratification.</p>
<p>If we were perfectly rational this wouldn&rsquo;t be that hard. Most bad
habits that have an instant reward now tend to have negative
consequences in the future, while good habits are the opposite. But
our brains are trained to prioritize instant rewards over delayed
rewards.</p>
<blockquote>
<p>As a general rule, the more immediate pleasure you get from an action,
the more strongly you should question whether it aligns with your
long-term goals. James Clear (Atomic Habits, P.189)</p>
</blockquote>
<p>To actually stick with habits it is important that their ending is in
some way satisfying. Similarly to <a href="/posts/habit_stacking/">Habit stacking</a>, where you attach the
beginning of a habit to something, it can be helpful to attach some
kind of reward to the end of one. This does not have to happen for
ever, since at some point the delayed gratification starts setting in,
making the immediate rewards obsolete.</p>
<p>An easy method to reliably stick with bad habits is to use a <a href="/posts/habit_tracker/">Habit
tracker</a>, making the progress easily measurable.</p>
]]></content>
        </item>
        
        <item>
            <title>Kultur</title>
            <link>https://wiki.jeykey.net/posts/kultur/</link>
            <pubDate>Thu, 21 Jan 2021 11:05:47 +0200</pubDate>
            
            <guid>https://wiki.jeykey.net/posts/kultur/</guid>
            <description>Viele versuchen aus politischen, religiösen oder finanziellen Gründen Kultur zu verändern. Aber was ist Kultur überhaupt? Ohne eine klare Antwort auf diese Frage ist es unmöglich, Kultur zielgerichtet zu verändern, da es für Veränderung die Möglichkeit geben muss, etwas zu messen. Nur so lassen sich vergleiche Anstellen und tatsächliche Veränderung feststellen. Ohne Definition lässt sich etwas allerdings nicht messen, daher auch nicht verändern.
Im Beschreiben von Kultur werden oft die gleichen Worte und Begriffe verwendet, wie wenn es um Personen geht.</description>
            <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Viele versuchen aus politischen, religiösen oder finanziellen Gründen
Kultur zu verändern. Aber was ist Kultur überhaupt?
Ohne eine klare Antwort auf diese Frage ist es unmöglich, Kultur
zielgerichtet zu verändern, da es für Veränderung die Möglichkeit
geben muss, etwas zu messen. Nur so lassen sich vergleiche Anstellen
und tatsächliche Veränderung feststellen.
Ohne Definition lässt sich etwas allerdings nicht messen, daher auch
nicht verändern.</p>
<p>Im Beschreiben von Kultur werden oft die gleichen Worte und Begriffe
verwendet, wie wenn es um Personen geht. Man könnte also stark
vereinfacht sagen, dass eine Kultur eine Sammlung von Personen ist.
Mit dieser Definition lassen sich zwar einige kulturelle Aspekte, wie
Traditionen oder Rituale zumindest teilweise erklären, sie beinhaltet
aber noch nicht die Auswirkungen die Gruppen (<a href="/posts/the_many/">The many</a>) von Menschen
mit einer gleichen Kultur auf Personen haben können.</p>
]]></content>
        </item>
        
        <item>
            <title>Implementation intention</title>
            <link>https://wiki.jeykey.net/posts/implementation_intention/</link>
            <pubDate>Thu, 21 Jan 2021 11:05:40 +0200</pubDate>
            
            <guid>https://wiki.jeykey.net/posts/implementation_intention/</guid>
            <description>A task is easier to do and quicker to become a habit if they have a specific trigger. An implementation intention describes the specific conditions and the situation that needs to exist, in order to trigger another task.
For habits it is best if the situation occurs regularly and the conditions apply broadly enough to allow frequent execution. But it is important, that it is specific enough to be directly actionable.</description>
            <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>A task is easier to do and quicker to become a habit if they have a
specific trigger. An implementation intention describes the specific
conditions and the situation that needs to exist, in order to trigger
another task.</p>
<p>For habits it is best if the situation occurs regularly and the
conditions apply broadly enough to allow frequent execution. But it is
important, that it is specific enough to be directly actionable.</p>
]]></content>
        </item>
        
        <item>
            <title>Habit perspective</title>
            <link>https://wiki.jeykey.net/posts/habit_perspective/</link>
            <pubDate>Thu, 21 Jan 2021 11:03:28 +0200</pubDate>
            
            <guid>https://wiki.jeykey.net/posts/habit_perspective/</guid>
            <description>Since we constantly run predictions, it is possible to change the outcome of these predictions, in order to change our perception of things. If you can change your view on them and turn them into something positive, something you get to do, there is nothing to overcome and you want to do them.</description>
            <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Since we constantly run predictions, it is possible to change the
outcome of these predictions, in order to change our perception of
things. If you can change your view on them and turn them into
something positive, something you get to do, there is nothing to
overcome and you want to do them.</p>
]]></content>
        </item>
        
        <item>
            <title>First principles</title>
            <link>https://wiki.jeykey.net/posts/first_principles/</link>
            <pubDate>Thu, 21 Jan 2021 11:02:47 +0200</pubDate>
            
            <guid>https://wiki.jeykey.net/posts/first_principles/</guid>
            <description>Early in our lives we learned some basic information and concepts from some higher authority. Without the ability to think about fundamental issues and complex concepts, this was the best idea for acquiring information.
But once we are able to think critically about the world this system becomes problematic. While it is the easiest and requires the least amount energy or critical reflection, it has a few fundamental issues:
 The information usually comes from some higher authority, hows interest may not be aligned with ours.</description>
            <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Early in our lives we learned some basic information and concepts from
some higher authority. Without the ability to think about fundamental
issues and complex concepts, this was the best idea for acquiring
information.</p>
<p>But once we are able to think critically about the world this system
becomes problematic. While it is the easiest and requires the least
amount energy or critical reflection, it has a few fundamental issues:</p>
<ul>
<li>The information usually comes from some higher authority, hows
interest may not be aligned with ours.</li>
<li>When something is new or there is no explanation by somebody else we
reason by analogy. This means we combine something we already know
or modify it in order to explain something new.</li>
</ul>
<p>A better strategy for understanding something new (and to understand
the world) is to break it down into its most basic components, its
first principles. If you dig deeper and deeper into a concept until
you are left with nothing but the most fundamental truths of the
situation, you have found the first principles.</p>
<p>First principles have a few key advantages over other thought-systems:</p>
<ul>
<li>Understanding the first principles of a situation will automatically
result in an understanding of the entire situation.</li>
<li>Once the first principles have been found they can be utilized to
create something new or understand something without having to rely
on any authority or external source.</li>
<li>By only thinking about the most fundamental units of a system a lot
of unnecessary items or distractions can be removed.</li>
</ul>
<p>Something similar can be observed in techniques like <a href="/posts/bisociation/">Bisociation</a>,
where objects aren&rsquo;t specifically broken down into their first
principles, but are still reduced and removed out of their previous
context, in order to form something new.</p>
]]></content>
        </item>
        
        <item>
            <title>Environment</title>
            <link>https://wiki.jeykey.net/posts/environment/</link>
            <pubDate>Thu, 21 Jan 2021 11:02:43 +0200</pubDate>
            
            <guid>https://wiki.jeykey.net/posts/environment/</guid>
            <description>In order to reduce the amount of triggers as well as the amount of self control needed to fight against them it is important to design your environment properly.
Once a habit is learned and internalized, it is unlikely to be forgotten. The only way to stop doing it is to remove the cues that trigger it.
This also works the other way around. If you want to learn a new (good) habit, it is possible to bind or connect it to an item in the environment.</description>
            <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>In order to reduce the amount of triggers as well as the amount of
self control needed to fight against them it is important to design
your environment properly.</p>
<p>Once a habit is learned and internalized, it is unlikely to be
forgotten. The only way to stop doing it is to remove the cues that
trigger it.</p>
<p>This also works the other way around. If you want to learn a new
(good) habit, it is possible to bind or connect it to an item in the
environment. This often happens with people. When the environment is
filled with negative influences it is easy to adopt their behavior.</p>
<p>Removing negative cues and influences from an environment is
important.</p>
]]></content>
        </item>
        
        <item>
            <title>Dunning Kruger Effect</title>
            <link>https://wiki.jeykey.net/posts/dunning_kruger_effekt/</link>
            <pubDate>Thu, 21 Jan 2021 11:02:35 +0200</pubDate>
            
            <guid>https://wiki.jeykey.net/posts/dunning_kruger_effekt/</guid>
            <description>„Wenn man inkompetent ist, kann man nicht wissen, dass man inkompetent ist […] Die Fähigkeiten, die Sie benötigen, um eine richtige Antwort zu geben, sind genau die Fähigkeiten, die Sie benötigen, um zu erkennen, was eine richtige Antwort ist.“– David Dunning
 Menschen können das Ausmass ihrer eigenen Inkompetenz nicht erkennen. Sie fühlen sich kompetent in Gebieten von denen sie keine Ahnung haben.Weniger kompetente Personen neigen dazu
 ihre eigenen Fähigkeiten zu überschätzen, überlegende Fähigkeiten bei anderen nicht zu erkennen, das Ausmass ihrer eigenen Unfähigkeit nicht richtig einschätzen zu können.</description>
            <content type="html"><![CDATA[<blockquote>
<p>„Wenn man inkompetent ist, kann man nicht wissen, dass man inkompetent ist […]
Die Fähigkeiten, die Sie benötigen, um eine richtige Antwort zu geben, sind
genau die Fähigkeiten, die Sie benötigen, um zu erkennen, was eine richtige
Antwort ist.“<!-- raw HTML omitted -->
– David Dunning</p>
</blockquote>
<p>Menschen können das Ausmass ihrer eigenen Inkompetenz nicht erkennen. Sie fühlen
sich kompetent in Gebieten von denen sie keine Ahnung haben.<!-- raw HTML omitted -->
Weniger kompetente Personen neigen dazu</p>
<ul>
<li>ihre eigenen Fähigkeiten zu überschätzen,</li>
<li>überlegende Fähigkeiten bei anderen nicht zu erkennen,</li>
<li>das Ausmass ihrer eigenen Unfähigkeit nicht richtig einschätzen zu können.</li>
</ul>
<p>Schwache Leistungen haben oftmals eine stärkere Verbindung zu
Selbstüberschätzung als starke Leistungen.<!-- raw HTML omitted -->
Umgekehrt unterschätzen fähige Menschen ihre eigenen Fähigkeiten.</p>
]]></content>
        </item>
        
        <item>
            <title>Diderot effect</title>
            <link>https://wiki.jeykey.net/posts/diderot_effect/</link>
            <pubDate>Thu, 21 Jan 2021 11:01:52 +0200</pubDate>
            
            <guid>https://wiki.jeykey.net/posts/diderot_effect/</guid>
            <description>The Diderot effect is most commonly used to describe spending habits. It describes how people often go into a spiral of spending after buying just a single expensive product. The effect, named after Denis Diderot (1713-1784), is made up of two components:
 Identity: If a consumer purchases an expensive good, his identity changes. After the first more expensive good he sees himself as somebody, that spends more on goods. Chain: Sometimes seeing that single more expensive item can look out of place.</description>
            <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>The <em>Diderot effect</em> is most commonly used to describe spending habits.
It describes how people often go into a spiral of spending after
buying just a single expensive product. The effect, named after
Denis Diderot (1713-1784), is made up of two components:</p>
<ul>
<li>Identity: If a consumer purchases an expensive good, his identity
changes. After the first more expensive good he sees himself as
somebody, that spends more on goods.</li>
<li>Chain: Sometimes seeing that single more expensive item can look out
of place. Some people then feel the need to purchase more and more
similarly expensive goods, in order to complement the initial one.</li>
</ul>
]]></content>
        </item>
        
        <item>
            <title>Decisive moments</title>
            <link>https://wiki.jeykey.net/posts/decisive_moments/</link>
            <pubDate>Thu, 21 Jan 2021 11:01:46 +0200</pubDate>
            
            <guid>https://wiki.jeykey.net/posts/decisive_moments/</guid>
            <description>If we look at our day as a decision-tree, we can see that each decision influences all that come after it.
Atomic Habits, Decisive Moments
With each decision we set the trajectory the rest of the day (or even beyond that) follows on.</description>
            <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>If we look at our day as a decision-tree, we can see that each
decision influences all that come after it.</p>
<p><a href="https://s3.amazonaws.com/jamesclear/Atomic+Habits/Media.pdf#page=15">Atomic Habits, Decisive Moments</a></p>
<p>With each decision we set the trajectory the rest of the day (or even
beyond that) follows on.</p>
]]></content>
        </item>
        
        <item>
            <title>Commitment device</title>
            <link>https://wiki.jeykey.net/posts/commitment_device/</link>
            <pubDate>Thu, 21 Jan 2021 11:01:39 +0200</pubDate>
            
            <guid>https://wiki.jeykey.net/posts/commitment_device/</guid>
            <description>The easiest way to break a bad habit is to make it impractical. This can be achieved by using commitment devices. (The opposite is also true: To achieve a good habit simply make it the preferred behavior.)
The key is to make it difficult to break the current good habit. For this it might be practical to automate the decisions, since humans are likely to fall for temptation.</description>
            <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>The easiest way to break a bad habit is to make it impractical. This
can be achieved by using commitment devices. (The opposite is also
true: To achieve a good habit simply make it the preferred behavior.)</p>
<p>The key is to make it difficult to break the current good habit. For
this it might be practical to automate the decisions, since humans
are likely to fall for temptation.</p>
]]></content>
        </item>
        
        <item>
            <title>Bisociation</title>
            <link>https://wiki.jeykey.net/posts/bisociation/</link>
            <pubDate>Thu, 21 Jan 2021 11:00:46 +0200</pubDate>
            
            <guid>https://wiki.jeykey.net/posts/bisociation/</guid>
            <description>In order to find new ideas it can be a viable strategy to think outside the realm of what is currently done or what is currently possible, because only those ideas will truly stand out.
In order to achieve this without building up an entire system from First principles, it can be a good strategy to combine two completely different items into something new. This might mean to apply a property of one onto another or create a completely item out of the combination.</description>
            <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>In order to find new ideas it can be a viable strategy to think
outside the realm of what is currently done or what is currently
possible, because only those ideas will truly stand out.</p>
<p>In order to achieve this without building up an entire system from
<a href="/posts/first_principles/">First principles</a>, it can be a good strategy to combine two completely
different items into something new. This might mean to apply a
property of one onto another or create a completely item out of the
combination.</p>
]]></content>
        </item>
        
        <item>
            <title>The economy</title>
            <link>https://wiki.jeykey.net/posts/the_economy/</link>
            <pubDate>Tue, 12 Jan 2021 11:07:47 +0200</pubDate>
            
            <guid>https://wiki.jeykey.net/posts/the_economy/</guid>
            <description>Our modern economy is mostly capitalistic (Capitalism) with a few twists:
 Some industries have strong government involvement. Very few people support the current system in it&amp;rsquo;s entirety (For some there is not enough government intervention and support, for others there is too much). When talking about the economy people don&amp;rsquo;t feel like they are a part of it (They think the economy is something bankers do).  </description>
            <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Our modern economy is mostly capitalistic (<a href="/posts/capitalism/">Capitalism</a>) with a few
twists:</p>
<ul>
<li>Some industries have strong government involvement.</li>
<li>Very few people support the current system in it&rsquo;s entirety (For
some there is not enough government intervention and support, for
others there is too much).</li>
<li>When talking about the economy people don&rsquo;t feel like they are a
part of it (They think the economy is something bankers do).</li>
</ul>
]]></content>
        </item>
        
        <item>
            <title>Motion or Action</title>
            <link>https://wiki.jeykey.net/posts/motion_or_action/</link>
            <pubDate>Tue, 29 Dec 2020 11:06:53 +0200</pubDate>
            
            <guid>https://wiki.jeykey.net/posts/motion_or_action/</guid>
            <description>Planning and strategizing about something can be described as being in motion. The steps are important, but they don&amp;rsquo;t produce a result. For that you need to take action.
Example:
 Planning to write a book and mapping out each chapter is motion. Actually writing it is action.  Why is it so hard to take action over motion? While in motion we feel like we are making progress without running the risk of failure.</description>
            <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Planning and strategizing about something can be described as being in
motion. The steps are important, but they don&rsquo;t produce a result. For
that you need to take action.</p>
<p>Example:</p>
<ul>
<li>Planning to write a book and mapping out each chapter is motion.</li>
<li>Actually writing it is action.</li>
</ul>
<p>Why is it so hard to take action over motion?
While in motion we feel like we are making progress without running
the risk of failure. If you are planning to do something you can&rsquo;t
fail. But if you act based on your plans you can fail. That&rsquo;s why only
being in motion is so attractive.</p>
]]></content>
        </item>
        
        <item>
            <title>Margin notes</title>
            <link>https://wiki.jeykey.net/posts/margin_notes/</link>
            <pubDate>Wed, 18 Nov 2020 11:06:46 +0200</pubDate>
            
            <guid>https://wiki.jeykey.net/posts/margin_notes/</guid>
            <description>When underlining and processing into the system is not enough to retain relevant information, margin notes can be used. They get you to think about the content while reading, meaning later context switching is easier or not at all necessary. Therefor margin notes should not be seen as a replacement or alternative to my personal reading system, but rather as an extension and tool to better utilize the current system.</description>
            <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>When underlining and processing into the system is not enough to
retain relevant information, margin notes can be used. They get you to
think about the content while reading, meaning later context switching
is easier or not at all necessary. Therefor margin notes should not be
seen as a replacement or alternative to my personal reading system,
but rather as an extension and tool to better utilize the current
system.</p>
<p>What to write:</p>
<ul>
<li>What ever thoughts or emotions the current line triggers.</li>
<li>Central ideas that the current point is related to (connections)</li>
<li>Summaries or keywords in order to make finding something in the book
at a later point easier (This functionality would also be fulfilled
by this indexing system, but some notes might not have been
transferred or aren&rsquo;t currently suitable).</li>
</ul>
]]></content>
        </item>
        
        <item>
            <title>Immanuel Kant</title>
            <link>https://wiki.jeykey.net/posts/immanuel_kant/</link>
            <pubDate>Wed, 23 Sep 2020 11:05:36 +0200</pubDate>
            
            <guid>https://wiki.jeykey.net/posts/immanuel_kant/</guid>
            <description>Moralität wurde historisch immer über Religion und Gott bestimmt. Aber ein solches System ist natürlich voller Probleme und Fehler die schnell offensichtlich werden. Es muss eingesehen werden, dass die allermeisten religiösen Moralsysteme fundamentale Probleme und Fehler haben. Da Menschen Anhänger verschiedener Religionen sind und selbst innerhalb einer Religion verschiedene Menschen verschiedene moralische Grundsätze haben, war es von Nöten eine andere, von Religion losgelöste Moral zu entwickeln.
Immanuel Kant (1724 - 1804) war einer der ersten, der Moral basierend auf Logik und Rationalität präsentierte.</description>
            <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Moralität wurde historisch immer über Religion und Gott bestimmt. Aber ein
solches System ist natürlich voller Probleme und Fehler die schnell
offensichtlich werden. Es muss eingesehen werden, dass die allermeisten
religiösen Moralsysteme fundamentale Probleme und Fehler haben. <!-- raw HTML omitted -->
Da Menschen Anhänger verschiedener Religionen sind und selbst innerhalb einer
Religion verschiedene Menschen verschiedene moralische Grundsätze haben, war es
von Nöten eine andere, von Religion losgelöste Moral zu entwickeln.</p>
<p>Immanuel Kant (1724 - 1804) war einer der ersten, der Moral basierend auf Logik
und Rationalität präsentierte. Nach Kant lässt sich das gesamte Interesse
unserer Vernunft in drei Fragen unterteilen:</p>
<ul>
<li>
<p>Was kann ich Wissen? Es geht um unser Erkenntnis der Wirklichkeit, um unser
Weltbild. -&gt; Ich kann das Wissen, was mir meine Sinne und meine Vernunft im
Zusammenwirken vermitteln. Wissen ist also ein Produkt von Sinnesdaten und
Vernunft. <!-- raw HTML omitted -->
Hier ist ebenfalls wichtig festzuhalten, dass Kant erkannte, dass unsere
Vernunft dem eingehenden Wissen auch immer eine bestimmte Form verpassten,
eine Art Filter darüberlegten. <em>Objektive Wahrheit</em> ist also für Menschen
beinahe unmöglich, da die Vernunft nie objektiv ist. <!-- raw HTML omitted -->
Auch hat Kant festgestellt, dass für Wissen sowohl Vernunft (Denken) als auch
die eigene Sinneswelt (Daten) von Nöten ist. Reines Denken allein ist also
noch kein Wissen. Während jemand über Gott oder die Unsterblichkeit nachdenken
kann, fehlen ihm die Daten um daraus tatsächlich Wissen zu machen. <!-- raw HTML omitted -->
Während Kant dafür bekannt war Träume und Hoffnungen zu zerstören sagt seine
These aber nichts über die Wahrheit der Aussagen aus. Nach Kant können wir
nicht wissen, ob Gott existiert aber wir können genauso nicht wissen, ob Gott
nicht existiert. Wer mit Wissen um kants Theorien immer noch an Gott glaubt
hat allerdings den Vorteil, dass sein Glauben unmöglich widerlegt werden kann.
Nach Kant:</p>
<blockquote>
<p>Ich musste das Wissen aufgeben, um zum Glauben Platz zu bekommen.<!-- raw HTML omitted --></p>
</blockquote>
</li>
<li>
<p>Was soll ich tun? Diese Frage war nach Kant die wichtigste. Es ist die Frage
nach gutem, moralischem Handeln. Nach Kant muss diese Moral auf Vernunft und
Logik basieren. Er nannte dieses System den <strong>kategorischen Imperativ</strong>.</p>
<blockquote>
<p>Handle nur nach derjenigen Maxime, durch die du zugleich wollen kannst, dass
sie ein allgemeines Gesetz werde.</p>
</blockquote>
<p>Der kategorische Imperativ gibt also keine absoluten Regeln oder Gesetze,
sondern liefert eine abstrakte Vorgabe für die Maxime unseres Willens. -&gt;
Handle so, dass die Maxime deines Handelns jederzeit als allgemeine
Gesetzgebung gelten können.<!-- raw HTML omitted -->
Mit den Maximen sind <em>Handlungsgrundsätze</em> oder <em>Prinzipien</em> gemein, die jeder
Mensch selbst hat. Man muss sich nach Kant also beim Handeln fragen, ob das
Prinzip hinter den aktuellen, eigenen Taten als Naturgesetz gelten könnte. Ist
dies der Fall, ist eine Handlung moralisch. Der kategorische Imperativ wird
auch manchmal <strong>Universalisierung</strong> genannt. Nach dem Prinzip: &ldquo;<em>Stell dir vor wenn
alle das täten.</em>&rdquo;. <!-- raw HTML omitted -->
Damit eine Maxime den Test der Universalisierung besteht müssen zwei Fragen
beantwortet werden:</p>
<ul>
<li>Kann man die Maxime wiederspruchsfrei als allgemeines Gesetz denken, nach
dem sich alle Menschen immer und überall verhalten müssen.</li>
<li>Können alle Menschen dies vernünftigerweise wollen?</li>
</ul>
<p>Wichtig ist, immer in Maximen und nicht in Taten zu denken. Es geht bei Kant
nicht um einzelne Vorhaben, sondern um Verallgemeinerungen und Prinzipien.<!-- raw HTML omitted -->
Auch gab es verschiedene Weiterentwicklungen, der wichtigste dabei ganz klar
der <strong>kategorische Rechtsimperativ</strong>.</p>
<blockquote>
<p>Handle äusserlich, dass der freie Gebrauch deiner Willkür mit der Freierheit
von jedermann nach einem allgemeinen Gesetze zusammen bestehen könnte.</p>
</blockquote>
<p>Man darf sich selber also als freien Menschen betrachten und niemand darf
einem Vorschreiben, was man Tun darf und Denken darf. Allerdings gilt dies nur
solange, wie die eigene Freiheit nicht die Freiheit eines anderen einschränkt.
Wann das der Fall ist bestimmt nicht ich oder die andere Partei, sondern ein
allgemeines Gesetz, welches für alle gilt.</p>
</li>
<li>
<p>Was darf ich hoffen?
Man darf alles hoffen, aber nur das Sinnvolle setzt sich durch. Um etwas
erledigt zu bekommen muss es also Sinn haben.</p>
<blockquote>
<p>Wer ein Warum zum Leben hat, kann fast jedes Wie ertragen.<!-- raw HTML omitted -->
Friedrich Nietzsche</p>
</blockquote>
<p>Um andere Menschen von einer Idee zu überzeugen muss es für jeden einzelnen
ein <em>Warum</em> geben. Für jeden muss es eine Chance geben, sich persönlich
weiterzuentwickeln, nicht nur für einen Chef die Arbeit erledigen.</p>
</li>
</ul>
]]></content>
        </item>
        
    </channel>
</rss>
